Cool.
Hello everyone and welcome to lecture 5
of CME 295.
So first of all, thank you all for
taking the time to take the midterm last
week. So I hope it was reasonable for
you. Um so for those of you who are
auditing in case you are interested in
taking the exam just know that the exam
and the solutions are both posted on the
websites
and um so now you know a little bit how
the exam looks like. So for the final
we'll have the same format except that
the content will be on lectures five. So
this one up until 9.
So I'll go down that point.
Cool. Uh great. So with that we're going
to start the lecture. So today we're
going to talk about LLM tuning.
So as usual we're just going to recap
what we saw last time. Um, so last time
was already two weeks ago, but we talked
about how to train an LLM. And in in
particular, we've looked at two
important steps. So the first one was
called pre-training
where you're basically taking a model
that has been initialized and you're
trying to teach the model about
language, about code. So you have this
step that is very time consuming,
expensive
um compute heavy that is happening on a
lot of data. So we've seen training
optimizations on how to make that
happen. So we've seen uh techniques to
parallelize that across GPUs. So we've
seen data parallelism methods and in
particular zero so the variant 0 1 2 3
and we've also seen very quickly what
model parallelism was in this case. So
at the end of this step what you obtain
is a model that knows about the
structure of language about codes
basically all the text that it has been
fed. But what this model can do is only
predict the next token.
So it's a great autocompleter,
but it's not a helpful model yet, which
is why we have a second step. And we saw
uh here it's typically called
fine-tuning or SFT for supervised
fine-tuning.
So here what we do is we take our
pre-trained model and we train it for
specific tasks.
So nowaday you have you know chat GPT
and all these like uh chat assistants.
So this can be one application. So
transforming your model into an
assistant. And so here the goal is to
teach the model how to behave.
So the model already knows what language
is, what code is, etc. And you're just
trying to make it behave like the use
case that you're trying to tune it for.
So typically here what you have is a
data set that is much smaller in scale
but of much higher quality
and you're basically tra uh taking your
model your pre-trained model and
teaching it exactly which tokens to
predict with the next token prediction
task.
And uh we've seen uh Laura which is
parameter efficient method which does
not tune all the weights but in a clever
way introduces low rank matrices that
are the ones that are being tuned
and we had stopped there. So what we're
going to see today is how to align the
model to align with what we call human
preferences.
And so here we're taking our model that
has been fine-tuned for a specific task
and trying to align our model to um make
it more something that a human would
like or that some metric that we're
defining would be more aligned with
that.
So as an example, let's suppose if you
have an assistant at the end of step
step two. So it's very much possible
that your assistant is you know behaving
the way you want but not let's say at
the tone that you want. So it's not
let's say friendly or it's not uh you
know safe. So you want to tune those
aspects in that third step.
Cool. So this step is called preference
tuning
and we're going to exactly see what that
is. So here for context let's suppose
that we have an SFT model and so by SFT
model I mean a model that has gone
through the pre-train stage and the
finetuning stage. And so for instance we
may ask our model uh to suggest a new
activity we could do with our teddy
bear. And here the model let's say
responds with I would suggest you to not
spend much time with your teddy bear at
all. So this is the response of an
assistant but it's not necessarily with
aligned with what we want.
So the idea here is to take these quote
unquote bad outputs and find
an output or rewrite an output that we
would want to have instead.
So this pair would be what what we call
a preference pair.
So in other words given this prompt we
have two responses.
One that we want to see which is this
one I'm going to read in a second and
then the other one that we do not want
to see.
So the for instance in this example the
answer we want to see is you know of
course teddy bears not only make awesome
companions for delightful sleep but also
can also be great buddies for fun
activities and you know just like
suggest some activities.
Does the setup sound good?
Yeah. So long story short we want to
align our model with human preferences.
So you may ask, you know, we have this
fine-tuning step already. Why would we
want to have a third step? Well, during
the second step, which is the
fine-tuning stage, if you remember, what
we did was construct a very high quality
data set of the kinds of prompts on
which we want our model to behave in a
certain way. So in order to compose such
a data set, it's actually something that
is very time consuming and very actually
difficult because the data set must be
of very high quality. And in this case,
what we're doing is not really teaching
the model exactly what it should
generate,
but rather telling the model what kind
of output it should prefer.
So we're less in a you know please
generate that kind of thing and more in
a you know I prefer this option kind of
thing.
And so typically, I don't know, if we
asked you uh write a poem, write a great
poem from scratch, it would typically be
much more difficult to do rather than
just showing you two poems, one bad poem
and one great poem, and ask you to just
say which one is better.
So in order to obtain the data sets,
it's already much easier.
The second reason is so during the SFT
stage when we compose our data set of
very high quality there is one aspect
that we really try to get right which is
the distribution of prompts
and what I mean by that is if we have
too much of a given kind of prompt our
model will be more biased towards
responding in that particular way. So
what people try to do is to be careful
about the distribution of prompts that
are in the SFT data.
And so here, let's say if our model
misbehaves, if we were thinking about
just adding one example in the SFT data
set, well, we would have to be very
careful about which prompt we're adding
and whether it's not going to bias the
model like too much in that direction.
So that's the second reason. And then uh
the third reason is what I mentioned
which is uh the SFT data is typically
very high quality. So if you're um
looking at all the missteps that your
model is doing and trying to put that in
the SFT data, you're just, you know,
have a hard time takes a lot of time. Um
but one note here
is if your SFT data is misbehaving a
lot, it may also be due to the fact that
your SFT data set has some problem.
So preference tuning is not the answer
to everything. Maybe it's better
sometimes to just check your SFT data
set for some issues.
That sound good? Yep.
Yeah. So to do that in the preference
tuning stage. Okay. So the question is
we saw Laura for SFT. What is the
equivalent for preference tuning? uh so
we'll see that later in the in the
lecture but you can think of Laura as
being some way to I guess reduce the
number of parameters that you need to
tune that is slightly different with the
objective function that you're using to
train your model and here preference
tuning you can think of it more as a
different objective function but it's it
may very well be something that you also
use LoRa for. So the two are not
incompatible.
>> Yes,
>> but it will become more clear later on.
But yeah, great question. Uh one last
thing I will add here is um another
difference with the SFT stage is that
preference tuning allows us to inject
some negative signal
because SFT is all about teaching the
model about like what it should predict
but it does not teach the model about
what it should not predict
and we will see that perference tuning
allows you to inject some negative
signal
Cool. So to start, of course, we need to
have our preference pairs. And so we're
going to look at this uh data collection
step first.
So here's the setup.
You have a prompt. Let's say write a
poem and you have a given response which
is the poem that is being generated by
the model.
You have a few ways to construct your
preference data.
So either you start with kind of a p
pointwise mindset where you score each
proposed poem with some kind of
pointwise score. And here pointwise
score means a score just relative to one
observation.
You could very well do that, but I will
say it's kind of hard.
It's kind of tough as a human to say,
okay, this one is, I don't know, 0.9,
this one is like a 0 2. It's not super
clear uh exactly how you would scale
that.
The second idea is for you to get two
observations at the time and for you to
say which one is better. So this one is
called pair-wise preference data and
it's much easier.
And then the third one is listwise which
is you know you get a list of let's say
n poems and then you just rank you know
which one is best which one is uh worse
etc etc and I guess this one is easier
than pointwise because you don't have to
specify I guess how much better it is
but I guess it's still a bit more
complicated
and that's the reason why people
typically use parise
So what they do is they collect
pair-wise preference data meaning for
each prompt they have two possible
answers and then
they just specify which one is better
and so that's the one we'll continue um
this lecture with. Okay so now you may
ask okay great uh pair wise preference
data but how do you get it?
Well, here is the recipe. So, in order
to generate a pair of responses, so
first you need a prompt and we've seen
um you know, previously I think it's
lecture probably three um that what you
could do was to generate different
answers if you have a temperature that's
positive. So typically what people do is
they put this prompt let's say twice
into the model with a positive
temperature and then they can get two
different answers.
Um the prompt is typically something
where we wanted to follow the
distribution of what the users typically
ask. So the prompt X can be something
that we obtain from the logs or from
let's say a desired set of prompts.
And then what we do is we have these two
observations. So the first one is the
prompt and the first response. The
second one is the prompt and the second
response. And what we do is we rate we
compare them.
So we can compare them with of course
human ratings
but we can also compare them with some
other metrics.
So I'll just list a few. Uh so we have
LLM as a judge which you may have heard
of which we have not seen yet which we
will see in a few lectures. That is also
typically used to just compare
I guess how much better one observation
is compared to another.
We can also use some other metrics
rule-based one like blur rouge etc.
Although it is not as used these days
and the simplest way to compare these
two observations is to have a binary
setting
where you say okay is response one
better or worse than response two. But
you could also think of a more nuanced
scale. Meaning you can also say okay
response one is much better, better,
slightly better, slightly worse, worse
or much worse. So this is also something
that you can do. Um but there are some
challenges with that approach
because for instance if you uh I don't
know consider human ratings a lot of
tasks are a little bit subjective.
So in a lot of cases actually what
people do is
having a pair wise preference data set
on the binary scale.
So only is it better or worse.
Does that sound good?
Yeah. Um okay. So another way to obtain
that data is
to have to find in your logs a response
that you did not like
to take that response and to rewrite it
which is basically what we did here. So
here when we have the response here what
we did is take the response and rewrite
rewrite a good one.
So this is also what people do but of
course it is a bit more involved because
you need to you know generate and I told
you that generation was uh kind of
costly and tough but this is also
possible.
Does the data collection make sense?
Yeah. Cool. Okay. So now we have our
preference data and what we want is to
align our model to prefer responses that
were preferred by the rating and I guess
down downweight the responses that were
not preferred.
And so in order to do that we will see a
method that's called RLHF RLHF.
And uh I'll see we'll see that uh in
more details in a second. Uh but as the
name indicates RLHF
relies on RL.
So I'm just going to start with some RL
basics. So do we have any RL experts
here?
Yeah. No. Okay. So no need to be an RL
expert. So don't worry, we'll go really
slowly on that.
So in the RL world world what people do
is they have an agent and here I mean
agent in the RL term which interacts
with an environment.
So what does it do? It is at a given
state at let's say time t. It can take
an action
at time t and it takes that action
according to some policy.
The policy is typically noted pi pi of
theta of the action given the state. So
what that policy means is simply
giving you the probability of you taking
an action given a state.
Easy, right? And so given that the agent
takes some action,
it also receives some rewards.
So sometimes it's a good reward,
sometimes it's bad rewards.
So what we're going to do is to leverage
that mindset
for our preference tuning exercise.
So let's see together how we can
transpose these quantities in the LLM
world.
So what is the agent?
The agent is the LLM.
So in terms of uh the state that it is
in so it's simply the input that it has
so far.
So the action that it wants to do is to
predict the next token. So it basically
always wonders okay what is the next
token given this input
and this action or this next token is
among the set of tokens that there are
out there. So if you want you know the
environment can be the set of tokens of
your vocabulary
and in order to decide which token
should come next.
The LLM determines that using the
probability of next token which is
obtained by you know when you do your
forward pass and when you look at uh the
probability distribution as an output
which is basically our policy.
So our policy here is simply equal to
the output of the LLM given the input in
order to determine the next token.
So far so good. And now we're adding one
additional thing. So I told you, you
know, we're composing our preference
data sets and we want to know which
output is better than the other output.
And so we're going to use that for a
reward. We're going to somehow use that
for a reward and we will see how we will
use that.
So I'm going to just recap that part. So
we have our LLM take some inputs and
then it wants to predict
the next token. It wants to take this
action. So in order to do that, it uses
the probability distribution that it
outputs
and then the token that it predicts or
the output that it generates then
receives some reward that is going to
feed back into tuning the agent. And
here's the LLM. Yep.
So the question is wouldn't that be
expensive if we do uh this for all
pairs? Why would that be expensive?
Mhm.
Uh yeah. So
yeah, the question is what do you do in
terms of how expensive that is? So yeah,
typically people take batches for
instance. Um but I would not so it is
indeed expensive but we're going to see
a little bit some order of magnitude and
how that works. But you can think of
this as uh being um kind of a training
procedure that could be seen as as
expensive as some other training
procedure. There's nothing that makes
this more expensive.
>> Okay,
>> but we're going to see exactly. So I
think you're there are some points that
you're you know touching correctly. Uh
there's some parts that are added
compared to the regular you know
supervised let's say supervised fine
tuning uh setting and we're going to see
that in a second.
H so the question is uh does the reward
that you're getting from here uh I guess
powerful enough for the LM to change
well you will see some expressions on
the internet just characterizing this uh
training procedure as you know like it's
nearly not as many signals as what you
would get for SFT let's say because for
SFT you're literally always taking a
partial input and making the LLM learn
how to um generate the next token. But
here you're only getting roughly one one
signal per completion. So yeah,
definitely it's more sparse and that's
why you will see that RHF is seen as
more an approach that has sparse
signals.
Yeah. Yeah.
Great question. So the question is, do
you apply reward for each token or for
the whole thing? We're going to see this
in more detail, but it's for the whole
thing. It's for the whole thing, but
we'll see that in uh in just a second.
Yeah.
So the AD and H. Oh, right. So the
question is what is the AT and ST? So uh
just as a reminder ST is the state that
you're in and 80 is the action you want
to take. So in the context of an LLM
uh the state that you're in for an LLM
is the input that you have that you have
so far and then the action is which
token you want to generate given that
input. Yeah.
Cool. Yeah. So far so good.
Okay, perfect. So now that we know a
little bit what a mental model could be
for I guess LLM based RL,
I just want to highlight once more that
what we're trying to achieve is learn
how to align this policy
with
rewards.
So we want to learn theta and theta is
the parameters of our LLM such that pi
of theta
align with preferences
and that's where RHF comes into play. So
RHF stands for reinforcement learning
from human feedback and it is typically
composed of two stages. So the first
stage is you
figuring out how to distinguish good
output from bad output.
So here you know all the preference
pairs that you collected are actually
used for you to learn what is good what
is bad. So the input here is the
concatenation of the prompt and the
response and the output is a score.
So what you want to know given a prompt
and a response how good that is.
And then the second step is the RL step,
the reinforcement learning step. And
this is where you use the rewards
to align your model with the
preferences. So here as input you have
the prompt and what you somehow want to
do is to be able to generate yhat that
is more aligned with the rewards.
And by the way I just want to call out
one thing. So RLHF is reinforcement
learning from human feedback.
The human feedback part
refers to the labels on which the reward
model is trained.
So if the preference pairs are based on
human ratings
then we're relying on human preferences
then we're in RHF
because you will see out there there is
also RL let's say Aif reinforcement
learning from AI feedback and that one
is relying on nonhuman preferences.
So yeah
cool. Okay, so now that we know what RHF
is and we know that there are two steps,
we'll go through the first step
naturally. So here the idea is we want
to construct a model that knows which
output is good, which output is bad. And
of course here what we want is to not
only consider the output but also the
input
because uh you need to somehow
contextualize that answer.
So let's go with the our favorite
example. Uh so let's suppose you have
the following prompt. Suggest a new
activity I could do with my teddy bear.
So what you want is to have a reward
model that here we note RM that tells
you that you know the answer that we
rewrote into the good answer is good
and we want to somehow have that model
that tells us that the output that we
constructed or that we did not construct
the output that we saw was bad is bad.
So we want to somehow have a model that
takes in the prompt and the good
response and say it's you know good and
we want to somehow have a model that uh
you know takes the prompt and the bad
response to say it's bad. So now the
question is how do you construct such a
model?
Well in order to do that we are using a
formulation that's called the Bradley
Terry formulation.
So that one is an important formula. So
uh we just stay here for a little bit.
So what it what it says is that the
probability bless you uh to have an
output yi
be better than an output yj
is equal to an exponential of some score
which is a score with respect to i over
the exponential of that score with
respect to i plus the exponential of
some 4 respect to J.
So that is called the Bradley Terry
formulation and this is the formulation
we will use to build our model.
So here um it's also equal to sigma of
RA I minus RJ. So who knows what sigma
is?
>> Yes, exactly. So it's a sigmoid. So just
as a reminder sigmoid is 1 / 1 +
exponential of minus x. So this is how
uh the graph looks like. So when it's
minus infinity it's uh it tends towards
zero and then when it's towards plus
infinity it tends uh towards one.
So in other words,
if I is better than J,
what we want is for the input to sigma
to be as high as possible
because you want the probability to be
as close to one.
So you want to somehow
have
R I be high if the output I is good.
and somehow our J to be low if the
output is bad.
So far so good.
So here
what we want to do is to somehow
train a model that is able to output
scores RA I and RJ
using this formulation.
So this formulation involves two
quantities because we have a pair-wise
data set.
So far so good. Okay. So it will become
more clear in a second. So here for
training the idea here is you have some
model that you initialize
and you input on the one hand your
prompt X and your winning output. So I'm
saying winning. So it's yhat W.
You put it into the model.
It produces score R of X and Y W.
And then you have a second output. So X
and Y L Y L which is the losing output.
So you put it into the model and it has
a second score.
And now you somehow want to have a loss
function
that takes into account these two
scores.
So based on this formulation,
do you have like a some suggestion as to
which loss function to use?
So here our loss function would be
parise.
Yep.
Yeah. Uh so the uh the proposed answer
is a binary cony. Um so can you explicit
that a bit more?
>> Mhm.
>> Uh-huh. Okay. So um I guess in that case
what would it be?
Yep.
Yeah.
Yeah. Yeah. Exactly. So I guess the Yes.
So great great answer. So I guess your
answer is having uh some negative log
likelihoods of this quantity which is uh
so the cross entropy can be seen as kind
of a special case of this but so just so
that that we make sure that we uh get
this part. Um
so in order to just get that uh
formulation which you mentioned again I
guess one idea that we can have is given
our data
and given this formulation that we saw
the Bradley Terry one
to find
parameters theta that maximize the
probability of that data happening which
basically leads leads to what you
mentioned. Uh so here I'm just going to
write what that means so that just we
can um kind of be all aligned. So here
it's
so let's suppose you have a preference
data set of let's say um you know
winning example associated with losing
example. So you have a bunch of pairs
like this. So let's suppose that these
pairs they happened independently of one
another. So what you want is to find
parameters that somehow maximize the
probability of you seeing
those examples.
Right? So here what that means is we
want to somehow maximize
the product of let's say these
n preference pairs which is the
probability of you know uh like some
output uh w being uh better than some
output l
and we saw that with the Bradley Terry
formulation. So we have this formulation
which is basically the product of
uh y I1 to n of this uh sigma of
this reward which is basically a
function of the input prompt and the
output
like this.
So what I'm doing here is to just
reconstruct the loss from first
principles.
So whenever you see a product of
probabilities, the first thing you need
to think about is
yes log because this can become very
small. So it can cause instabilities. So
if you take the log, if you want to
maximize a product is the same as
maximizing the log of that. So if you
take the log of that. So let's suppose
I'm taking let's say the log of that.
Let's say I'm taking the log of that.
So it's basically equal to the sum
of the log of
sigma of r of the winning
minus the one from the losing.
So we want to maximize that.
But people in ML they like to minimize
things. So we're going to take like have
a negative in front. So maximizing plus
the sum of the log is the same as
minimizing minus the sum of the log. And
so this
will be our loss function.
Does that make sense?
And this is exactly what you mentioned.
And
typically we uh you know write the
expectation
and this is our loss function.
So our last function is minus the
expectation of log of sigma r and x and
y y w minus the reward of the losing.
Sounds good. So here the last function
is pairwise
but the reward model is it pair wise or
is it pointwise
like I guess do you need a pair to make
a prediction or do you need just one?
>> Do you need a pair
pair? Well that's the beauty of things.
You don't need a pair. So you're just
training it pair-wise but it's actually
pointwise.
So I think that's one thing I kind of
realized. You know I look at this loss
and you know this is a beautiful thing.
So you're training in a pair wise way,
but at the end of the day, you have a
reward model that takes in one prompt
and its output and just outputs one
number.
And we saw that it will try to output a
high score for, you know, winning um
examples and then a low score for losing
examples.
So this is our reward model. And I'm
looking at the time. I'm actually not on
time, so I'll just move on. Um, so
typically here what you would need is a
set of data, which is typically on the
tens of thousands or maybe even more.
Um, and here the label would be the
preference rating. The preference here
should come from humans if we're talking
about RLHF.
And in terms of model, well, you have a
bunch of different choices. Uh so as we
know now uh models that are decoder only
that predict the next token are very
popular. So you could very well take
such an LLM and just have some
classification heads at the end of your
sentence that you're uh taking into
consideration and then use that to
predict the reward. Or if you remember
uh we've also seen encoder only models
uh in the beginning of the class. So for
instance BERS you could typically also
project the embedding of the CLS token.
This could very well be an option.
So typically what people do nowadays
is take the LLM route because everything
is an LM these days. So it's like
decoder only. You just put a
classification head.
And so people have also come up with
benchmarks
to evaluate how good you're doing. So
just put a reference here. Reward bench
in case you're interested is a pretty
popular one.
Um
but yeah,
so at the end of this you get a reward
model that takes in a prompt and a given
response
and gives you a score.
Yep.
>> Exactly. So the question is uh in some
tasks the human preference would be
something but in other tasks it may be
something else. So typically those
rewards they are with respect to a given
dimension.
So they can be let's say is the output
useful
or is the output I don't know friendly
is the output safe. So all of that are
different dimensions. So they can be
different reward models.
Um you can also have like some holistic
score as well.
uh but yes so you need to define a
dimension across which you're actually
quantifying how good your response is.
So the ones that I mentioned are uh the
common ones that you would you would
find. Um another thing that I will say
as well uh while we're at it so human
ratings are very sensitive to the
guidelines that you're also exposing.
So, we're not going to go into details
here, but one important aspect of human
preference data is to make sure that the
guidelines you're telling your raiders
are as objective as it could get. I
mean, sometimes you cannot have them be
super objective, but you you have the I
guess the task of just making sure
they're clear enough so that your human
preferences
uh they're not noisy because they can be
noisy, but that's also one challenge.
Yep.
So the question is uh is the reward here
like a regression or a classification.
So let's look at the
at the loss function and here.
So well it's kind of hard I guess I
would say um because the reward can be
kind of something that can be
interpreted as a score but we have a
probabilistic formulation
um so I'll probably frame that as a
classification task because you have
preference data is it better worse so
it's like one or zero but at the end you
use the rewards so it's not I
purely a classification task because at
the end you have this um but one thing
to note is that the scale that these
rewards are at is typically something
that is scaled itself.
>> So at inference time you have some
normalization procedure that normalizes
that across your batch but yeah I would
probably characterize the formulation
more as a probabilistic one I would say.
Yep.
Yep. So the question is do we normalize
the score? So there are many different
methods to I guess normalize things. We
typically do. We typically do normalize.
So I guess if you're in a regression
setting, you're trying to predict some
score on a given scale, which you're
you're not doing here. So it's kind of
free form here.
Um so yeah, so there is some rescaling
that happens. Yeah. You had a question.
>> Yeah. The question is uh can you tell us
more about what a the output of a reward
model is? So we're going to see that a
bit later but you can think of you know
good outputs as being let's say one bad
outputs as being a minus two minus
three. So it's basically on the
continuous scale if you want.
We're going to see an example in a
little bit. So hopefully this can Do you
have a question? Perfect. Uh we're going
to see an example. So hopefully that
will be clear.
Cool. Um
so what we did is train a reward model.
Now the second step is to use that
reward model to align our model or and
by model I mean the LLM. The LLM that
went through the pre-training stage and
the SFT stage is the model that we want
to align with human preferences.
We're going to do that using
reinforcement learning and we're going
to do that using the reward model that
we just constructed.
So the reward model here
is the model that we obtained in step
one and it allows us to distinguish
good outputs and bad outputs.
So here is a general recipe of how you
would align your model.
So first you would take your prompt
as input.
Your LLM will generate
a completion.
So here a completion means like a full
response from the model. So by the way
completion people use also the term roll
out. So it generates a completion, a
roll out, a full response
and that full response along with the
prompt
goes into the reward model.
So as we saw the reward model right now
knows if it's a good, if it's bad. Let's
say right now it's bad. So in practice
it does not generate the the thumbs
down. It generates some kind of score.
So if you if you want like minus two,
let's suppose.
So we take that reward into
consideration
and then what we do is we tune the LLM
with this information.
So it's more complicated than that and
we'll see how we go about doing this but
this is the general idea.
So just as a reminder, the reward model
is the model that we trained as step one
and it is a model that is frozen.
We're not training the reward model. The
reward model has been trained.
The model that we're training is the the
LLM.
So I think that's an important point to
note.
And our goal
is to optimize for higher rewards
but then
without going too far from the initial
model.
So I think the you know optimizing for
higher rewards I think everyone agrees
with me right. But I I I just said a
second statement which is but we don't
want to go too far from the initial
model.
So why would that be like why would we
want to not deviate too much from the
base model?
So one suggested answer is it will
catastrophically forget what it has
learned. Why would that be a problem?
great. Yeah, I think it's a great way to
put it. So the the the suggested answer
here is uh you have all this knowledge
in your initial model which is
pre-trained and then instruction tuned
or tuned and you don't want to move away
too much. This is exactly it. So that's
one reason.
What could be another reason? So
definitely one, it's a very very good
reason. What could be another reason?
Yeah.
Yeah. So uh overfeeding on that data. So
can you tell me more?
>> Yeah, great point. So the second
suggested answer is uh you can overfeit
on a data that is not super clean. And I
will go a bit more into detail on what
that means.
Yep. You want to add?
Yeah. Yeah. Exactly. So I guess your two
points are I guess along the same lines
which is the reward model can be noisy.
So that's exactly it. So, it's a
phenomenon that's called reward hacking
where
if you are trying to optimize too much
for the rewards, you're basically
assuming that the reward is exactly
quantifying what you want, but it may
not be the case because the reward model
itself is imperfect.
So just to make sure that everyone gets
the point going to illustrate that with
an an example. Um so let's suppose that
I'm giving a lecture
and my objective is for the lecture to
be as informative as possible.
So I can take the choice to have
something that I can quantify to know if
what I'm saying is informative. So let's
suppose if my reward is uh how loud the
claps are at the end of the lecture if
the clapping is very is a lot or not.
The problem is if I optimize too much
for the volume of clapping at the end.
It may be the case that if I found out
that you all like jokes and I start
making jokes and then you clap at the
end, you know, my reward is maximized
but my objective is not fulfilled which
is make the lecture informative.
So in practice, this reward hacking
phenomenon
is something that leads your model to
optimize too much
on a metric or a score that is
imperfect. So you can very well maximize
the rewards but not fulfill what you
want. And this is exactly what the idea
behind reward hacking is.
So yeah and another reason by the way.
So it's one reason is because uh your
base model is already great. it knows a
lot of things. Second one is because the
reward model is imperfect. So you have
this reward hacking phenomenon. The
third reason is also because you can
have some training instabilities.
Anyways, we have a bunch of reasons why
we don't want to deviate too much.
And so in this setup, you typically have
more observations than in the reward
model case. So you have typically at
least 100k observations
and the label that you get here is from
the reward model
and uh so you start with the model that
you obtain that's after SFT. So that's
the one that you train. And the last
function will be something that will try
for you to maximize the rewards, but
also
to not have you deviate too much from
the base model. So we're going to see
exactly how we can do that. But that's
the idea of how our loss function will
look like. It will have these two parts.
Sounds good.
And as we saw uh so we don't want it to
deviate too much because of reward
hacking and instability and and so on.
So in order to do that you may have
heard a very popular RL algorithm that's
called PO.
So PO stands for proximal policy
optimization.
So the reason why it's named proximal is
because we do not want our model to
deviate too much from the base model and
we're going to see how we do that.
So this is roughly how our loss function
will look like. So we'll have a part
that is a reward model that we want to
maximize and then some other part that
is around
uh measuring how far the distribution of
the policy that we're training
is to the reference model or the base
model. So here the reference model would
be
your SFT model.
So you have these two parts.
Does the formulation of the loss roughly
make sense so far? That make sense?
Cool. Uh okay. Kale divergence. Um so
I'm just talking about Kale divergence,
but I don't want to just assume you know
what that is. Um so the Kale divergence
is
some measure. I don't want to say
distance because distance has a lot of
connotations to it. It's not a distance
but it's some measure of how far two
probability distributions are.
So you take a probability distribution
let's say P and another one probability
distribution Q and you compute this um
formula which is the sum of PI log of PI
over QI just gives you a number of how
distant or how far these two
uh probability distributions are.
So you want to minimize
the loss.
So, I guess you want to minimize
how far they are.
Um,
does that make sense that we're using
this? Yeah. Um, okay. So, just one
little question. So, okay. Is the K KL
divergence positive or negative or like
what what can you tell me about the KL
divergence?
Have you seen the Yeah, it's positive.
Why is it positive?
Yeah, but why?
So maybe we can come later. But great,
great. I think the, you know, the result
is here, but I guess I want to know why.
Yes.
Ah, yes. Exactly. So yeah, if you use
Jensen's inequality because uh when you
look at this formula, I mean luck can
take like positive and negative values.
It's not super clear, but uh yeah, the
the way you prove that it's always
positive or equal to zero is with the
Jensen's inequality.
Um and so yes, this quantity is equal to
zero if and only if P and Q are equal.
Cool.
So with that, we're going to go a little
bit more in depth into
um the loss function. So I mentioned
that the loss function tries to maximize
for rewards
but also make it so that the model does
not deviate too much from the base
model.
Well, there's something that I've
like kind of lied a little bit about
you, which is we don't want to maximize
rewards. We actually want to maximize a
quantity called advantage.
So what is the advantage? So you can
think of the advantage as being how much
better is your output compared to what
you would expect.
So people typically use advantage to
make the whole process be I guess more
stable the training more stable
and we estimate that advantage with a
function called the value function which
we will see in a little bit. Did you
have a question? No, no question. So we
we we have two quantities right? We have
the reward that we saw previously how to
compute which is given a prompt given a
completion
how good is this you know prompt and
and then the value function is another
estimation
but this estimation is not at the
completion level is actually at the
token level.
So what we're doing here is we're taking
the prompt along with the partial
generation as input
and we're trying to estimate
what the reward would be if we were to
continue to generate the output
following the policy.
So I'm just going to repeat this one
more time because it's charged in
meaning. The value function is a token
level estimation
of the rewards that takes in a partial
input and predicts the reward.
So
if that predicts a reward if you were to
follow the policy in your generation.
So this value function is something you
will see in papers as something that
people have to train when they do PO and
it's typically because people need to
have this value function when they
compute the advantage that I mentioned
above
and this value function
is typically trained jointly with the
policy.
So in other terms you have your LLM
which is initialized as the SFT model
which you know generates the prediction.
So what you typically do is also have
some head value head
that also
so this time is not a classification
problem it's a regression problem. you
try to estimate the final reward if you
were to continue to generate according
to policy.
So this is typically something that you
also need to train jointly with the
policy
and I am intentionally not going too
much into detail as to exactly how that
advantage is formulated. It is just
beyond the scope of this class. But in
case you're interested, I would highly
recommend reading this paper which is uh
mathematically involved about the
generalized advantage estimation methods
which people typically use for this. So
it's this highdimensional continuous
control using generalized advantage
estimation paper. If you if you're
interested just feel free to take a
look. But this is typically the method
that people use to estimate these
advantages.
So now we're going to see in a second
where those advantages are used. But
just as a high level, does that make
sense to everyone? What we're trying to
achieve here?
Um yeah. So um in other words, what we
want is to maximize the rewards but not
deviate too much from the base model.
But what we want is to actually
find a way to
make the rewards a bit more relative as
to what you would actually expect.
So you want to compare the rewards that
you're obtaining
with kind of an average response if you
want like the idea is okay if you are
having a great reward what would be the
reward kind of in the average case and
you want to still maximize that
and the reason why people use this
reward minus baseline is because it
reduces the variance of these estimates
and it just makes the training just kind
of go faster typically. So that's why
people use that part.
But in order to compute the advantage,
what people use is a method called
generalized advantage estimation which
you can think of it as like a big
formula with some hyperparameters.
Uh that is in the paper below.
Just a general idea.
Cool. So, okay, looking at the time. So,
we're going to look at two typical
variants of the PO loss.
The first one is called PO clip.
So, the idea here
is to prevent the updates to our model
from being too large from one iteration
to the next.
So what you have is this loss
formulation
which is the minimum of
the ratio and we're going to see what
that is times the advantage and some
clipping of that ratio between two uh
bands which we're going to see in a
second times that advantage.
So before we go into details, I just
want to call out a few things that may
seem like it's confusing because it was
confusing to me. Um so first of all
that formula is expressed as L is equal
to but it's actually not something we
want to minimize something that we want
to maximize.
So what people typically mean by L is
loss.
Um so yeah just know that we want to
maximize that we don't want to minimize.
The second thing is we're introducing a
term called R of theta.
This is not the reward model.
So typically people use R to say it's
the reward but here it's not the reward.
It's actually the ratio in the
probabilities between our policy
and the policy from the previous step
which is denoted pi old pi theta old.
So it quantifies
how different your policy at the current
stage is to your old policy.
So here when we say old,
it's not
the SFT model. It's not the SFT model.
It's the model at the previous iteration
during the RL stage.
Because here, what we want is for the
policy to not have updates that are too
wide.
So far so good.
Yeah.
What is a? Uh a is our advantage.
So you can think of it as you know this
complicated formula that's a function of
the reward and the value function that
just tells you how good your uh your
your piece is basically.
Okay. So this um complicated formula
we're just going to see why it makes
sense.
So
if the advantage is positive,
it means that we somehow want to
reinforce whatever was generated.
And so here our objective function will
look like this. So if a is positive
then this L of clip will look like some
linear function as a function of R
because it's R * A.
So it's a it's a linear function as a
function of R and then after 1 + epsilon
it will just be flat.
So why why do we want such a such a
shape for our graph? Well, we need to
think again about what R means. So if A
is positive,
meaning it's something that we want to
reinforce,
we typically want the probability of
whatever happened to be increased.
So we want R
to be higher,
but we don't want it to be too too high.
So that's why we have this clipping
mechanism.
So that's why we have this uh this
clipping here. We want to I guess
maximize L. So we go uh towards
increasing R. But we don't want to
increase it increase R too much.
So that's the rational for this.
But when a is negative,
it means that somehow what we've done is
something that we don't want to do as
much.
So in order to uh maximize L, what we
want is to actually
decrease the probability
of just generating what we generated. So
we want R to be
smaller because it also increases L, but
we don't want it to be much smaller. We
don't want too big of an update, which
is why we have this clipping mechanism
here.
So in other words, this super
complicated formula can be just
intuitively explained with what I just
mentioned,
which is if you have positive
advantages,
you want to reinforce
the fact of generating this output
because this is something that the model
liked. I mean the by model I mean the
reward model. Um but you don't want it
to update it too much which is why you
have this clipping and same when the
advantage is less than zero. Um I guess
you want to downweight
the probability of this output from
happening. So you want to have a smaller
R which is your ratio between the policy
you're training with respect to the old
one. But you don't want to be too small
either again to not make too big of an
update.
Does this make sense?
Does this roughly make sense? Okay,
roughly makes cool. Just I will just um
recommend just rereading this formula.
I'm just uh remembering what I mentioned
and hopefully it would make a bit more
sense. Um but yeah, happy to answer any
questions if there are any. Yeah. Oh,
yeah.
Yes.
Yeah. Uh so question is uh what happens
uh where it's not continue. It's the
same as ReLU, right? Like you you would
basically use the same methods. Um so
yeah, it's the same same thing. Yep.
So great question. question is why are
you using from the previous iteration
and not the base model? Because actually
we don't want just to not be too far
from the base model. We also want our
updates to be not too extreme from one
iteration to another. And this is to uh
improve with uh stability of training.
So this is just like another additional
constraint we want.
uh question is are we considering the
base model? We will consider it and I
will tell you exactly but u in this in
this formulation we're not in this
formulation we're not but in the
formulation we're using typically for
LLM based RL we are and we will see how
Yep.
Yeah. Yeah. Yeah. So the question is how
do you quantify R like what is R? What
does it mean? So it's typically u the
probability of a token happening with
respect to the input. So you can think
of the probability distribution that you
get at the output of your LM. So you
would use that.
Cool. So this is the first variant that
the PO paper mentions. So it's called PO
clip.
So the second variant that we have is
the one that uses KL divergence which is
called KL penalty. And this one is a
function of the ratio times the
advantage minus
the K divergence between
the old policy which is the previous
iteration and the current iteration.
So you had a great point which is why
are we using the old? In fact, old means
previous RL iteration. But nowadays,
people use the reference. So, it's just
a change because this paper has been
published in 2017 where in 2025
LLMs, they kind of came more into like
something that was popular in the 2020s.
So, um, so yeah, there's just been this
like difference in what you put there.
So yeah, it's indeed the reference that
you would typically put in a Kyle
divergence.
Uh the other thing that I will say is
that
nowadays when someone wants to train uh
a policy using PO, they would typically
use the kale divergence and they would
also maybe mix it with the clipping
clipping thing with the old iteration.
they were basically mix the two.
There are many different formulations of
what the loss can be. So what I'm saying
is not always true, but this is what
people sometimes do. They sometime mix
the two.
Cool.
So, I talked to you about PO and how it
allowed you to maximize
rewards, maximize advantages
by not making your model deviate too
much from the base model and also from
the previous iteration.
But the problem is that for PPU, you
need a lot of models.
So you need your policy, you need your
LLM that you're training. You also need
the value function which I me which what
I mentioned is is used for the advantage
estimation.
You also need the reward model
of course and then you need the base
model. So the base model is frozen. It's
the just the SFT model just to be able
to compare with the current policy. So
it's a lot of models.
So now the question that you may ask is
do you really need to have all these
models to perform well?
And the answer is maybe not. Maybe but
maybe not. And nowadays there is a bunch
of other methods that are becoming more
popular. So you may have heard of GRPO
in the context of reasoning models. So
we will look at GRPO in more detail next
week for lecture six. Um but just know
that there are many variants. So PO is
just one algorithm that has been very
popular and even within PO there's been
many variants and nowadays there are
many other RL algorithms
that are being used.
Yeah.
And uh yeah if you want to just uh
anticipate next lecture um you can also
take a look at this paper from uh the
deepseek team. So deepse math limits of
uh mathematical reasoning in open
language models that introduces the gRPO
algorithm. But if you don't it's fine
we're going to talk about it next week.
So I also want to talk about some
challenges when it comes to
RLbased approaches.
So the first one is you need to have
this two-stage process. You need to
first train your reward model and then
you need to use the reward model to
train your policy.
But the problem is you do step one, you
do step two and then you realize, oh
wait, step one has a problem. then you
need to redo everything. So there is
like a bunch of dependencies that that
can really you know make your life
harder and um you know just the training
recipe is not the simplest. So that's
one downside.
The second downside is about the number
of hyperparameters that you need to
tune. So we saw beta from the Kyle
divergence formulation. So that's one.
We have epsilon from the PO clip
version. That's another one. The
generalized advantage estimation. We
have not seen the formula, but there's I
think at least two hyperparameters that
I can think of.
Anyways, you have a bunch of them.
So of course, you know, some
hyperparameters perform better than
others. And you know, if you need to
retrain, then well, you need to do
everything again.
um then you have some instability
challenges. So you know you can
constrain your iterations to not be too
wides to kind of control for that but
sometimes it's not uh you know
sufficient.
So in terms of the metric that you can
use to monitor the training, what what
is the metric you would use?
So we're trying to maximize rewards in
some sense. So typically the metric that
you would use to monitor your training
would be the average rewards.
But this is not like a great I mean this
is a way to to you know monitor your
training but this is not like the best
way necessarily.
So at least when it came to pre-training
and SFT you had this cross entropy loss
that you were monitoring that was really
telling you how your model was able to
you know just reproduce the behavior you
were trying to make it uh output.
But yes, so this is another challenge.
And then the other thing is
in the RL world, in order for you to
know which completion you should not do
and which completion you should do more,
you need to have some diversity
whenever you generate. So if during the
RL training loop, every time you have a
prompt, you generate something and then
you retry and you generate something
else that's too close.
Well, it's not it's not great because
you're not exploring the set of possible
completions. So this is another
challenge you need to have in mind which
is you need to force your model to do
some exploration to see I guess what can
be good.
Um, and then the last point is
I mean a lot of you were not familiar
with RL. I was not and it's not super
clear why we would necessarily need need
RL to do this stage.
Um, also I will say one thing. So this
RLbased training you will hear a lot the
term on policy training. I just want to
tell you what that means. So what is
different between this and SFT is during
SFT we had some prompt and some response
that we wanted our model to generate to
mimic.
But here what we're doing is at each
iteration
we're asking our model to generate an
output and then we're using how good
that output is to update our model. So
there is a core difference between the
two because in here what we're doing is
we're asking the model to generate
something
whereas for SFT we're just using some
you know some data that is not
necessarily generated by our model.
So on policy training refers to training
that involves the model generating from
its current policy and optimizing on
that.
And this is in contrast with off policy
training which is relying on generations
that are not done by the model that
you're training.
Does this make sense?
Yeah. So this is a term you will see a
lot which is why I'm telling you. Um and
yeah so PO is an on policy
algorithm.
Yeah.
So the question is why don't we do SFT
on this preference data? Well SFT you
you tell the model you should generate
this given this input. then you should
generate this given this input. But
you're not telling it about things it
should not generate.
Like let's suppose you have something
that you don't want to happen unless you
rewrite that into you know a perfect
sentence. There is no way for you in a
traditional SFT framework to tell your
model to not generate that.
But that being said, it's a great prompt
because later on in let's say 10
minutes, we will see a supervised way of
doing what we did with RL.
But yeah, it will be in about 10
minutes.
But apart from that, does that roughly
make sense?
Yeah,
perfect. So in the next few minutes we
will see a method that is actually used
more often than not and this is for
people who have a reward model but that
don't want to do RL.
So why do you not want to do RL because
you know it's expensive it's you need a
lot of models. So to your points it's
indeed expensive because you need all
these like models and you know sometimes
it's just too hard to tune that
training. So you have this method called
best of n or bun
and the idea here is to leverage the
reward model that you obtained in order
to choose the output that you will
return to the user.
So the idea here is
you have a prompt
and you tell your models okay I you
actually want to have several um
generations. So you generate let's say I
don't know four times five times and
what you do is you give a score to each
prompt completion
and you just return the best one the top
rated one
which is why it's called best of n. So
you have n completions you rate all of
them and you just return the best one.
So you have your prompts. So, uh, our
favorite example suggests a new activity
I could do with my teddy bear. You put
it into your SFT model. So, you're not
training your SFT model. It's asis
and you're just generating, let's
suppose, three completions. Uh, the
first one is a great answer. The second
one is no, don't spend time with the
teddy bear, which is not a good answer.
And then the third one, I think it's
also a good one, take your teddy bear to
a picnic. You put all of these into your
reward model and this is where I wanted
uh to respond to you like you know what
is an output of the reward model. So it
would be a score like this. So for
instance the first one would be you know
pretty good uh completion. So it's like
0.8 the second one is not good at all.
Let's say minus two and the third one is
like let's say so so in between.
So the best of end method would select
the top rated one which is the first one
and this is the one that you would
return.
Okay. So
what is one problem with this approach?
So the the answer is uh if the model is
bad then it's going to be bad. That's
fair. But I guess if you uh make enough
completions with let's say a high enough
temperature, you will have some
diversity.
Um so it's it's a fair point uh which
can be a problem. But let's suppose it's
it's indeed a problem. Let's suppose
it's not a problem. What is another
problem that you may have?
Yep.
Yes. Yes. So the answer is uh you query
the model many times which is indeed the
problem. So you write inference what you
want is to not spend a bunch of money
and compute but here what you're doing
is uh complete your prompt multiple
times
and this is indeed the main challenge
with this. So you indeed skip
the RL training but you're basically
pushing all the work to your inference
to the inference stage
and uh this is just making everything so
super costly. So when can it be bad? So
um if for instance you're in a in a case
where you need to serve your model to
let's say a bunch of traffic it may not
make sense for you just um just from a
cost standpoint.
So um I would say before taking that
route it may be good to just assess what
will be your inference traffic what
would be your training cost and kind of
uh determine that from there.
And um yeah, I think that's pretty much
it. Do we have any questions on that
part?
Oh yeah. Yeah.
Um that sigmoid would be softmax. Are
you talking about this one?
Um
so in that algorithm you're assuming
that your reward model is is trained.
So uh the best of end approach is you do
this this training. So I guess the sigma
here is uh pairwise because you trained
your model in a pair wise fashion.
Um but in the best of end um case what
you do is you just use your reward model
to score end times and you just pick the
the the highest one. Yeah.
Yep.
>> Yeah. The question is uh but what if all
the responses are bad? This is
definitely a fair a fair concern. Uh and
this is indeed a concern. So your model
needs to be at least a little bit good.
Yeah. Yeah. Yeah. Yeah. Exactly. Yeah.
Yeah.
It's a great question. And do you have
any constraint on the scale? Well,
depending on how your scaling is done,
you actually don't care about the scale.
As long as you take the best one, the
highest one, if you think about it,
let's suppose if you scale it with,
let's say, with a normal score, the
highest one will still stay the highest
one. So in this case, you actually do
not care about the scale.
Yes, you also don't care about that.
Yep. But typically the scaling matters
when it is coming into play in a loss
function which is the case for RL
and so that's where people use some like
scaling mechanism. Um you know that's
that's the part that matters.
Cool. And with that I'm going to give it
to Shervin.
Thank you.
So, for this last part, we're going to
talk about DPO.
Um, but I'm not going to tell you what
DPO means just yet. We're just going to
first um listen to the complaints we had
in the RL world and then see um what we
could do about it and then how have
folks um like remedied it.
So the first thing that I'm going to
repeat from one what Afinen covered is
that in the RL formulation of PO
you have to carry during your loss
optimization a bunch of model weights.
So when you look at this um loss
function you have uh so first the policy
of the current model you have to
optimize for the one of the old model or
the reference model uh and then you have
your advantage which hides the reward
model as well as the value function that
we discussed. So like all these four
which is a lot
and uh the second thing is that let's
say you go with the approach of best of
end you don't do RL you just generate
multiple times uh and then like pick the
best completion as Ein mentioned and um
so you have this uh latency and cost
issues and just uh for the sake of you
know thoughts uh for a thought
experiment. Let's suppose we had
infinite money. Would it be still fine?
Um so let's suppose you generate all of
these in parallel.
So you would still need to um wait for
the maximum time of like the generation
of an answer to give your resulting
answer. And then if you look at the
distribution of latency, usually it's
some you know shape that is not centered
on a single point. And when you look at
the probability distribution of the max
of let's say n answers, it will tend to
be uh shifted to the right. So let's
suppose you have infinite money,
infinite compute,
um you still have to wait more than you
would have on a single pass.
Do these concerns make sense?
And okay, so there comes the question
that someone was asking. Why don't we do
supervision all this time? And this is
the route that uh DPO folks have
explored. So DPO stands for direct
preference optimization. So instead of
doing this uh expensive two-step process
of first finding some reward model and
then uh iterating on the model's
weights, it optimizes a single loss
function that directly optimizes for the
model's weight. And as you can see, uh
there is no reward involved anymore. So
no R. and you have a way to formulate
what you care about as a function of
your preference pairs. So in that loss
function all you have is a bunch of
variables and then the sigmoid functions
but within uh the parenthesis you have
the probability of a given completion
like to happen and uh you have this uh
subtraction operation that compares the
probability of the winning uh completion
to happen versus the losing one. So as
you can see it's a direct expression
with respect to these preference pairs
which is pretty nice
and if you look at it a bit closer you
will recognize what I've just mentioned
regarding Bradlary
formulation because you have this uh
expected value of log of a sigmoid and
then within that sigmoid you have a
difference of terms where you can
recognize the equivalent of what you saw
as a reward term.
So I know it's a lot to see at once. The
formula is not super pretty. Um yeah, do
you have any questions?
And then we're going to discuss in a bit
what that beta is and also how we
obtained this formula in the first
place.
Uh okay. And I one thing I will mention
before going to that is that the paper
is titled your language model is
secretly a reward model. And the reason
for that is that the reward um like
placeholder that you could identify from
this loss function is expressed as a
function of your policy. So you don't
have any Rs in there. But when you
express the equivalent of a reward, you
find the expression of your model um of
your model directly. So which is um kind
of pretty interesting insight.
Okay. So but but now let's think
together about how we got there in the
first place.
So you recall from a few few slides ago
the PO objective that we had. So we
wanted to maximize
uh rewards and minimize the distance of
the obtained policy with respect to the
reference one which is this uh trade-off
between maximizing rewards and scale
diver divergence term. And then you have
this beta coefficient that appears there
that uh controls
how how much you want to penalize going
further from the base model. And what
this paper did is that it wrote down
this formula and then solved what would
be the optimal solution. Uh so it
expressed the optimal policy pi star and
when you derive this expression so you
get it as a function of r. So that's
other term that was in the objective
function
and uh so like all these steps have no
extra assumptions. It's just a bunch of
uh derivations that was done. And uh
what you can see here is like this Z
term that stands for a partition
function and that just normalizes things
uh but it's not something that is new.
It's like a function of the other uh of
the of the terms that were already in
there.
So when you rearrange these terms you
can uh equivalently
express R as a function of this pi star.
Uh so it's just like a rearranging terms
between these two expressions. Nothing
um nothing too fancy.
And then uh the key part of of what this
paper did is recognize this term as some
reward and then
express it as part of a Bradley
formulation. So you remember you had
this probability of um of a completion
of a winning completion being bigger
than a losing completion and you had
this sigmoid of uh like the difference
between the two Rs. So basically they
took this formulation again and they
plugged in the expression they had
obtained for the optimal reward which we
had seen was a function of the policy.
So at the end of it you plug in things
you have no more rewards just a function
of the other parameters. So you have
this beta and uh only the the policy in
there.
And the last step is the same one as
Afin was mentioning. Once you have this
probability that you want to maximize
you can turn it into a loss function.
And this loss function is what this
paper proposes to optimize in order to
tune
policy weights in order to align it with
this preference data.
So yeah, I simplified a lot the quite
heavy steps of this paper uh into like
this these few steps. Do they make
sense?
And uh the beta that we see here is the
same beta as we had seen in the PO
formulation. So typically taken um
around 0.1 if you want some order of
magnitude. So beta is a hyperparameter
and all you want to optimize for is the
policy and then the preference pairs you
have them as input.
Make sense?
Okay, great. So now let's compare uh
what this method gives with respect to
RHF.
Um so RHF is this two-stage training
process where you first fit a reward
function and then use it uh in order to
do the policy update steps. So as Afin
was mentioning it, it's quite heavy. Um
we were mentioning it just before you
need a lot of models in memory and then
training stability is is a concern. You
don't have direct supervision. You rely
on the policy of the current model to
generate the next updates. So there is a
lot of complexity in it and as opposed
to that this DPU formulation gives a
supervised way to think about preference
tuning where you just take these
preference preference pairs and you
directly fit a loss function on them
and um yeah and then instead of four
models you just need two because you had
this pi of theta and then a pi ref which
was your base SFT model and you don't
need any other model copi copies.
So now you might want to ask um if it's
um if it's much easier, why um why is
not everyone just simply using DPO? So
it's not as easy. Uh in practice um
there are some pros and cons to each
method. Um and the paper that is listed
below uh gives a very interesting study
of um you know like the benchmarking
differences and the steps to get there.
Uh so just to get the main lines overall
PO performs better than DPO. Um and um
one great thing about DPO which is like
this supervision this direct supervision
comes at the cost of sometimes fitting
something that is not the exact
distribution that the model has seen as
training time. So this paper talks about
it a bit. um if you train via SFT on the
preference related data, you could get
better performance. But this shift in
distribution is uh you know a challenge
intrinsic to to DPO.
uh because one thing that the DPO method
enables you uh to have is just to not
worry about that reward modeling at all
and just get some preference data set
out there. But the issue with with doing
so is exactly that distribution shift.
Uh so you could you know either train uh
like SFT on it or generate it yourself
and then rate it but that is u like yet
another cost that you would need to uh
to pay.
Okay, great.
Um and
yep, any questions?
Uh so the question is uh you are
optimizing the parameters with respect
to the base model. So yes but it's not
the base model it's the current one. You
have a base model that will stay fixed
in the iterations and that occurs in the
loss function and you're indeed uh
updating parameters and that will be
like the preference tuned one. Yeah. So
you have like two weights two set of
weights one frozen one one that you
update. Yep. Okay, great.
Any other questions?
Yes. So the question is uh instead of
the reference model, could you use
another model uh another large model? So
I think that is a that's an interesting
point.
I guess that would be a different
algorithm.
Um, and you might lose a bit the meaning
of what you're trying to do because this
preference tuning stage is trying to
align your responses to what you prefer
and you want them to align with respect
to what you had learned so far. So if
you like start from a different model
and then you preference tune like a
different probability distribution, you
might be doing things that might not
make as much sense from a loss
standpoint. But I guess you know the
direction I mean I I cannot tell like a
blanket answer there. You know, maybe it
could give like interesting behavior,
but my intuition would tell you that the
point of all of this is to start from
the last train checkpoint that you had
and then further like preference tune
the distribution of your completions,
>> right? So like the the suggestion was
you know if you change the reference
model that could be seen as another SFT
uh version of your model. Yeah I guess
so.
Okay great. And now the favorite my
favorite part of of today. So do you all
remember the completions we had obtained
on our favorite prompts? So can I put my
teddy bear in the washer? So if you
remember last episode we had said uh
after instruction tuning the response
was no it might get damaged try hand
washing it instead.
So does anyone have any complaints
regarding this answer?
So I can give a hint teddy bears they
indeed should be handwashed. So, it's
factually correct.
But let's suppose it's factually
correct. What else do you not like? I
mean, could you not like about this
answer?
Yeah. So, the suggestion was uh is
asking to try it instead. And I guess
like a broader point is it's a bit too
rough, doesn't sound super friendly. And
then you know someone who asked this
question might love teddy bear. So did
you want you might want to tell them
about it in a gentle way. And uh this is
exactly what a preference tuning stage
is about. We don't want to learn new
facts. We want to focus on the existing
distribution of completions and align
what the model should return with
respect to what the human prefers.
So on this intuition, the preference
tunes answer could be um like a gentler
one. It's better not to your teddy bear
could get hurt. Uh gentle hand wash is
safer. So it's conveying the same points
but in a tone that's uh that sounds like
much better to the ears of of the person
who asks.
Okay, great. Any questions on the DPO
part?
Yep.
Yeah. The question is um like what are
the trade-offs and then which one is
used in practice. So I think it all
depends on your compute budget on how
much you want to worry about performance
versus babysitting your training
process. PO like the RL bar is very hard
to tune right. It will give the highest
uh results. Uh but you might get almost
at that level with much less efforts. So
I guess if you want to get like a quick
preference tuning that is shown to like
show good results but maybe not not the
best results and DPO is your is your
friend. And if you're an expert at uh
reinforcement learning, you you know
what you're doing and you want the every
last bit of performance, then PO might
be like a better way.
Okay. Amazing. And with that, thank you
very much.